<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-detnet-ip-oam-02" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.6.0 -->
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<front>
    <title abbrev="OAM for DetNet over IP">Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) for Deterministic Networks (DetNet) with IP Data Plane</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-detnet-ip-oam-02"/>
    <author initials="G." surname="Mirsky" fullname="Greg Mirsky">
      <organization>ZTE Corp.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
        <email>gregory.mirsky@ztetx.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D" surname="Black" fullname="David Black">
      <organization>Dell EMC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>176 South Street</street>
          <city>Hopkinton, MA</city>
          <code>01748</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>david.black@dell.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>DetNet  Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>DetNet</keyword>
    <keyword>OAM</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	   This document defines the principles for using Operations, Administration, and Maintenance protocols and mechanisms in the
	   Deterministic Networking networks with the IP data plane.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
   <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/> introduces and explains Deterministic Networks (DetNet)
   architecture.
      </t>
      <t>
       Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) protocols are used to detect, localize defects in the network,
       and monitor network performance. Some OAM functions, e.g., failure detection, work in the 
       network proactively, while others, e.g., defect localization, usually performed on-demand.
       These tasks achieved by a combination of active and hybrid, as defined in <xref target="RFC7799" format="default"/>,
       OAM methods.
      </t>
      <t>
   <xref target="I-D.tpmb-detnet-oam-framework" format="default"/> lists the functional requirements toward OAM for DetNet domain. 
   The list can further be used for gap analysis of available OAM tools to identify
   possible enhancements of existing or whether new OAM tools are required to
   support proactive and on-demand path monitoring and service validation.
   Also, the document defines the  OAM use principals for the
	   DetNet networks with the IP data plane.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Conventions used in this document</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
The term "DetNet OAM" used in this document interchangeably with longer version
"set of OAM protocols, methods and tools for Deterministic Networks".
</t>
        <t>DetNet    Deterministic Networks</t>
        <t>DiffServ   Differentiated Services</t>
        <t>OAM:      Operations, Administration and Maintenance</t>
        <t>PREF      Packet Replication and Elimination Function</t>
        <t>POF        Packet Ordering Function</t>
        <t>RDI         Remote Defect Indication</t>
        <t>ICMP      Internet Control Message Protocol</t>
        <t>   Underlay Network or Underlay Layer: The network that provides
   connectivity between the DetNet nodes.  MPLS network providing LSP
   connectivity between DetNet nodes is an example of the underlay layer.</t>
        <t>DetNet Node - a node that is an actor in the DetNet domain. DetNet 
   domain edge node and node that performs PREF within the domain are 
   examples of DetNet node.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Keywords</name>
        <t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
   "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
   described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> 
   when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="oam-data-plane" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Active OAM for DetNet Networks with the IP Data Plane</name>
      <t>
OAM protocols and mechanisms act within the data plane of the particular networking layer.
And thus it is critical that the data plane encapsulation
supports OAM mechanisms in such a way that DetNet OAM packets are in-band with a DetNet flow
being monitored, i.e., DetNet OAM test packets follow precisely the same path as
DetNet data plane traffic both for unidirectional and bi-directional DetNet paths. 
</t>
      <t>
The DetNet data plane encapsulation in a transport network with IP encapsulations specified
in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC8939" format="default"/>.
For the IP underlay network, DetNet flows are identified
by the ordered match to the provisioned information set that, among other elements, includes the IP protocol, source port number,
destination port number. Active IP OAM
protocols like Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) <xref target="RFC5880" format="default"/> or STAMP <xref target="RFC8762" format="default"/>,
use UDP transport and the well-known UDP port numbers as the destination port. Thus a DetNet node MUST be
able to associate an IP DetNet flow with the particular test session to ensure that test packets experience the
same treatment as the DetNet flow packets.
</t>
      <t>
Most of on-demand failure detection and localization in IP networks is being done by using the Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP)
Echo Request, Echo Reply and the set of defined error messages, e.g., Destination Unreachable, with the more detailed information provided through code points.
<xref target="RFC0792" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC4443" format="default"/> define the ICMP for IPv4 and IPv6 networks, respectively. Because ICMP is another IP protocol like, for example,
UDP, a DetNet node MUST able to associate an ICMP packet generated by the specified IP DetNet node and addressed to the another IP DetnNet node
with an IP DetNet flow between this pair of endpoints.
</t>
      <section anchor="ip-udp-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Active OAM Using DetNet-in-UDP Encapsulation</name>
        <t>
Active OAM in IP DetNet can be realized using DetNet-in-UDP encapsulation [Ed.note: Do we define it in this document or start a new one?].
Using DetNet-in-UDP tunnel between IP DetNet nodes ensures that active OAM test packets are fate-sharing with the monitored
IP DetNet flow packets. As a result, a test packet shares the tunnel with the IP DetNet flow and shares the fate, statistically speaking, of the IP DetNet flow being monitored.
</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="native-ip-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Mapping Active OAM and IP DetNet flows</name>
        <t>
IP OAM protocols that use UDP transport, e.g., BFD and STAMP, can be used to detect failures or performance degradation that affects an IP DetNet flow.
When the UDP destination port number used by the OAM protocol is one of the assigned by IANA, then the UDP source port can be used to achieve co-routedness
of OAM, and the monitored IP DetNet flow in the multipath environments, e.g., LAG or ECMP. To maximize the accuracy of OAM results in detecting failures and
monitoring performance of IP DetNet, test packets should receive the same treatment by the nodes as experienced by the IP DetNet packet. Hence, the DSCP
value used for a test packet MUST be mapped to DetNet.
</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="over-gre-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Active OAM Using GRE-in-UDP Encapsulation</name>
        <t>
<xref target="RFC8086" format="default"/> has defined the method of encapsulating GRE (Generic Routing Encapsulation) headers
in UDP. GRE-in-UDP encapsulation can be used for IP DetNet OAM as it eases the task of mapping an OAM test session
to a particular IP DetNet flow that is identified by N-tuple. Matching a GRE-in-UDP tunnel to the monitored IP DetNet flow
enables the use of Y.1731/G.8013 <xref target="ITU-T.1731" format="default"/> as a comprehensive toolset of OAM. The Protocol Type field
in GRE header MUST be set to 0x8902 assigned by IANA to IEEE 802.1ag Connectivity Fault Management (CFM) Protocol / ITU-T Recommendation Y.1731.
Y.1731/G.8013 supports necessary for IP DetNet OAM functions, i.e., continuity check, one-way packet loss and packet delay measurement.
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!--
<section anchor="hybrid-oam" title="Use of Hybrid OAM in DetNet">
<t>Hybrid OAM methods are used in performance monitoring and defined in <xref target="RFC7799"/> as:
<list>
<t>Hybrid Methods are Methods of Measurement that use a combination of
   Active Methods and Passive Methods.</t>
   </list>
   A hybrid measurement method may produce metrics as close to passive,
   but it still alters something in a data packet even if that is the value of a 
   designated field in the packet encapsulation. One example of such a hybrid measurement method
   is the Alternate Marking method (AMM) described in <xref target="RFC8321"/>. One of the advantages
   of the use of AMM in a DetNet domain with the IP data plane is that the marking is applied to a data flow,
   thus ensuring that measured metrics are directly applicable to the DetNet flow.
   </t>
</section>
-->

<section anchor="ip-over-tsn-sec" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>OAM of DetNet IP Interworking with OAM of non-IP DetNet domains</name>
      <t>
A domain in which IP data plane provides DetNet service could be used
in conjunction with a TSN and a DetNet domain with MPLS data plane to deliver end-to-end service.
In such scenarios, the ability to detect defects and monitor performance using OAM is essential.
<xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls-oam" format="default"/> identified two OAM interworking models - peering and tunneling.
Interworking between DetNet domains with IP and MPLS data planes analyzed in Section 6.2 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls-oam" format="default"/>.
Also, requirements and recommendations for OAM interworking between a DetNet domain with MPLS data plane and OAM of a TSN
equally apply to a DetNet domain with an IP data plane.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
  This document does not have any requests for IANA allocation. This section can be deleted before the publication of the draft.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
   This document describes the applicability of the existing Fault Management and
   Performance Monitoring IP OAM protocols,
   and does not raise any security concerns or issues in addition to ones common to networking or
   already documented for the referenced DetNet and OAM protocols.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ack" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgment</name>
      <t>
TBA
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0792.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8086.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-detnet-mpls-oam.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8939.xml"/>
        <!--
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6310"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7023"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-ip-over-mpls"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-ip-over-tsn"?>
   -->
    </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informational References</name>
        <reference anchor="ITU-T.1731">
          <front>
            <title>Operations, administration and maintenance (OAM) functions and mechanisms for Ethernet-based networks</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2015"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="G.8013/Y.1731"/>
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7799.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8762.xml"/>
        <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8321"?> -->
    <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5880.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-tpmb-detnet-oam-framework.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
